<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An oration gratulatory to the high and mighty Iames of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, King, defendor of the faith, &amp;c. On the twelft day of February last presented, when his Maiesty entered the Tower of London to performe the residue of the solemnities of his coronation thorough the citie of London differred by reason of the plague: and published by his Highnesse speciall allowance. VVherein both the description of the Tower of London and the vnion of the kingdomes is compendiously touched: by William Hubbocke.</title>
            <author>Hubbock, William, b. 1560.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A03780</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 13899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104268</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840007</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840007</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4475</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A03780)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4475)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1417:06)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An oration gratulatory to the high and mighty Iames of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, King, defendor of the faith, &amp;c. On the twelft day of February last presented, when his Maiesty entered the Tower of London to performe the residue of the solemnities of his coronation thorough the citie of London differred by reason of the plague: and published by his Highnesse speciall allowance. VVherein both the description of the Tower of London and the vnion of the kingdomes is compendiously touched: by William Hubbocke.</title>
                  <author>Hubbock, William, b. 1560.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Barnes, and are to be sold in Paules Church-yard at the signe of the Crowne [, London], by Simon VVaterson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1604.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Latin text followed by English text.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-B⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4475:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4475:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ORATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ON GRATVLATORY TO the High and Mighty IAMES of <hi>England, Scotland, France and Ireland, King, Defendor of the</hi> faith, &amp;c. On the twelft day of February laſt <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented, when his Maiesty entered the Tower of</hi> London to performe the reſidue of the ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties <hi>of his Coronation thorough the citie of London</hi> differred by reaſon of the plague: and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>by his Highneſſe ſpeciall allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>VVherein both the deſcription of the Tower of London and the vnion of the kingdomes is compendiouſly touched:</hi> By WILLIAM HVBBOCKE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>AT OXFORD,</hi> Printed by Joſeph Barnes, and are to be ſold in Paules Church-yard at the ſigne of the Crowne, by <hi>Simon VVaterſon.</hi> 1604.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:4475:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>POTENTISSIMO IACOBO AN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliae, Scotiae, Galliae, &amp; Hiberniae Regi, fidei <hi>Defenſori, &amp;c. Oratio duodecimo Februarij, cum Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cem Londinenſem ingrederetur, vt inaugurationis ſuae reliquas ſolennitates per vrbem perageret, dila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas ob graſſantem peſtem, gratulatoria; eiuſque au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spicijs praelo mandata.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In qua &amp; totius Turris ſuccincta deſcriptio, regnorum<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> vnio perſtringitur:</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Authore <hi>Gulielmo Hubbocke.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:4475:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">D</seg>ABO ait Dominus per Hoſeam Prophetam <hi>vallem</hi> Achor <hi>pro fori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ſpei.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Oſea. 2.15.</note> Erat autem vallis <hi>Achor</hi> primus aditus <hi>Iſraeli</hi> in promiſſam terram. Et hoc quidem vallum (po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiſſime Rex) eſt veſtibulum ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> terrae promiſſae tibi: et primum inaugurationis tuae veſtigium, ad regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tibi coeleſti decreto ante te natum deſtinatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ius ad has valvas ſalutant te meis verbis, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum locum hic tenens tuus fidiſſimus, belli paciſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> orname<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tis illuſtris miles, tota<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> armata cohors circumſtipantium regium latus tuum, ſervientes hoc loco tui: <hi>ſed conſalutant</hi> vno nutu, <hi>Anglia</hi> tota, Gallia, <hi>Hibernia,</hi> quaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnium <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premumius, huius</hi> vnius loci complexu prenſas, &amp; quaſi manu tenes. Haec enim arx, hoc caſtrum regale, arra eſt omnium: &amp; porta non modo bonae ſpei, ſed portus totius rei. Hic magnificae &amp; regales beſtiae, <hi>leones Anglicani,</hi> ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t <hi>leone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scotiae;</hi> ô verè de leone <hi>Iudae</hi> oriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, ô verè atavis edite regibus: Hic numiſma cuditur, nervi &amp; artus belli, quod Caeſareum tuum nome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vultum iampride<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> geſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit: Hic chartophylacium regni, ſcrinium actorum &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plomatum principum noſtrorum, illuſtriſſimoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum tuorum, ê quibus emendatior hiſtoria, auſim dicere, quam quae vlla extat, perpoliri poſſit. Exiſtunt hic etiam circumquaque, per anfractus huius loci, ſparſae rotundatae turres ad ſontium laeſae maieſtatis cuſtodia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: vna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hanc citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam
<pb facs="tcp:4475:3"/>
maiores noſtri ſanguinolentam dixere, ob cruo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem, vt aiunt, infa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Edouardi</hi> quarti, quos <hi>Richardus</hi> terti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us execra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dae memoriae, horreſco referens, immaniter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trucidavit. Proſtat inde officioſè in te deſuper ſpectans, ſed aheneis tormentis propoſitis flammarum vomitus &amp; tonitrua hoſtibus minitans, grandiuſculum &amp; quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Martis propugnaculum, robur loci, vigil vrbis, cuſtos pacis, moderator circumiacentis regionis, cuius caniciem facies ipſe atteſtatur, in quo priſca fama Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni <hi>Caeſaris</hi> praecipuè aulam concelebravit. Hic gemma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum domus &amp; gaza regni, innumera complectens maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mi pretij vtenſilia, totam<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> auream &amp; argenteam ſupel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectilem vnà cum opulentiſſima re veſtiaria regia, quae omnia ſeſe in ſinum tuum vt iuſtiſſi ni domini &amp; hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redis ex aſſe iamdudum effuderunt. Hic, ne ſingula co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorem, globorum monticuli: armorum ſupra, infra, ampliſſima domicilia, bombardis, ſpiculis, haſtis, arcubus ſagittis, loricis, galeis, pulvere tormentario, toto deni<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> apparatu militari, equeſtri, pedeſtri, terreſtri, navali, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fertiſſima: ad hoſtes tuos ſubiugandos, ad amicos, cives, ſubditos, ſocios &amp; foederatos tuos defendendos: ad pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricula, iniurias, vim, metum à capite tuo (fortiſſime Rex) à corde tuo, chariſſima clariſſima<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Regina, à liberis, à fortunis, à toto comitatu propulſanda. Quamobrem gratias, quantas animus noſter capere poſſit, ei inprimis habemus,<note place="margin">Prov. 9.15.</note> 
               <hi>per quem Reges regnant,</hi> per quem amplitudo tua, <hi>Iacobe apud</hi> alios <hi>ſexte</hi> in hac ſexta aetate mundi, apud nos prime, in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtanti aetate tua, nuta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te aetate Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni noſtri regnum init, &amp; regnat: &amp; quidem quod in tam diſſitis ſtudijs, diſſectis ſectis, diſtractis animi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, incredibili omnium ordinum aſſenſu, vnoquoque acclamante, nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo reclama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te, ſine omni caſtrenſi ſtrepitu ita pacificè reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net.
<pb facs="tcp:4475:3"/>
Nulla regio, municipium, praefectura, vrbs, pagus, ex quo non publice venerunt, omniu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> generum, aetatum, ordinum, omnis fortunae &amp; loci, etiam ex remotiſſimis gentibus legati, gratulatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Quantae effuſiones hominum ex oppidis, concurſus ex agris patrum-familias cum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iugibus &amp; liberis, quaſi dei immortalis dies feſti &amp; ſolen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes agerentur. Vt non maior fuerit <hi>Iſraelis</hi> &amp; <hi>Iuda</hi> olim officioſa concertario ad reducendum <hi>Davidem</hi> Regem ſuum, quàm eſt noſtrum totius Regni,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 19.</note> tanquam vnius vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri, praeſtò obſequium ad inducendum <hi>Davidem</hi> noſtrum ſecundum cor Dei regem.</p>
            <p>Nam quae duo in <hi>Davide</hi> eximia fuerunt, artis &amp; mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ornamenta, domi piae doctrinae laus prophetica, in bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo fori arma victricia; hae virtutes duae iam coepêre eſſe tuae, qui &amp; ſine bello ſuperbos debellans, ampliſſima reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, ipſo audito nomine, aſſequeris, &amp; in <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> piaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> artiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; politioris literaturae, eos verè aureos libellos co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcripſeris, vt bonae literae; quae antea veluti plebeiae, ſpretae apud multos iacebant, iam nobilitari &amp; te regnante reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nare videa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur. Eſt autem vt in coeli medio Sol pulchrior quam vlla alia in parte: ita in regali perſona eruditionis ſplendor illuſtrior, fructus copioſior, quam in reliquo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ordine: Cum inde et iuſtitiae praeſes, et ſcholae prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceps (vt nuper ad noſtru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnium decus) ipſe eſſe poſſit, tum ad ius ſuis oculis pervidendum, tum ad literas fove<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, et literatis favendum multo amplius. Et quanquam non poſſumus non affici ſummo deſiderio <hi>Divae Elizabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thae;</hi> tamen cùm, illâ maturo die ſuo,<note place="margin">Viam lacte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am in caelo, var j com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res Iacobi viam dixe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re.</note> vt ſole noſtro occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dente et abeunte à nobis, ita brevis &amp; ſerena nox ſit inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſita, tot regniluminibus vnam viam Regiam, tanquam coeleſtem galaxiam et planè <hi>Iabobaeam</hi> deſignantibus il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrata: aliuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ita mane nobis exortus ſit Sol, cuius bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficio,
<pb facs="tcp:4475:4"/>
adeò pulcher iam hic integer fermè annus, tanquam vnus dies illuxit, nobis ſine vlla nubecula tempeſtatis ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futurae, niſi quae in ipſa coitione Dei preſidio evanuit: vt nihil niſi <hi>Elizabethicum</hi> in hac rerum co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>verſione ſentia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, nec in poſteru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> niſi bona omnia <hi>Elizabethica</hi> de ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtate tua expectemus, pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erquam quod maſcula tua virtus &amp; viriles dotes, maiora quaedam &amp; auguſtiora pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liceantur: Deo, cuius in faemore ſcriptum eſt, <hi>Rex Regum &amp; Dominus dominantium,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Apoc. 19.16.</note> principi Electorum tuoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (nam non hominis hoc factum ſed numinis) gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimis animis acquieſcimus; in te vncto Dei (ſacroſancte Rex) conquieſcimus. Haec eſt enim omnium congratula<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium lo et triumphalis ovatio noſtra.
<q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Martial.</note>Vox diverſa ſonat, populorum est vox tamen vna:</l>
                  <l>Tu Rex, tu patriae diceris eſſe pater.</l>
               </q>
Quare arceſſe tibi pacis triumphos; capeſſe claues regni, clavum imperij teneto: poſſideto principatus tui came<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram &amp; metropolim <hi>Londinum:</hi> conſcende hanc terrae a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cropolim &amp; armamentarium praecipuum, turrim <hi>Londi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nenſem.</hi> Hibernia praeſaga tui partim ſubacta, partim dedititia tua facta eſt. Roſae duae Anglicanae, &amp; <hi>Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrenſis</hi> vere rubens, quia vulneribus ſuis cruentata, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauſta propè erat: &amp; <hi>Eboracenſis</hi> recte albicans dicta, quae amiſſo bellis inteſtinis ſanguine, ad mortem ferè ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>palluit, &amp; quae ambae coniunctis aculcis, ſaepiù<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> quam par eſt, compungentes, cum <hi>Leone Scotiae</hi> conflictatae ſunt, iam vt corollae &amp; ſerta capitis tui ſe offerunt. Tanquam Deus iam complêſſet, quod vaticinatus eſt olim per <hi>Eze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chielem</hi> in hanc ſententiam: <hi>Tu fili hominis, cape tibi duo ligna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 37.16.</note> 
               <hi>in vno inſcribe</hi> Iehudae; <hi>in altero inſcribe</hi> Ioſepho <hi>cum tota domo</hi> Iſraelis: <hi>tum compinge ea in vnum, vt ſint vnum in manu tua. Nam ſic ait</hi> Iehova: <hi>accepturus ſum
<pb facs="tcp:4475:4"/>
domum</hi> Ioſephi <hi>cum tribubus</hi> Iſraelis, <hi>&amp; domum</hi> Iehudae, <hi>cum tribubus eius, &amp; componam eas coniunctas in manu mea, &amp; efficiameas gentem vnam: &amp; Rex vnus nempe</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid <hi>ſervus meus paſtor erit illis, ne<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> erunt amplius duae ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, nec dividentur amplius in duo regna.</hi> Quis non videt hic amat<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> ſimilem dei nutum? Improbi, myrmillones, buſtuarij putabant in interregno turbam in turbas conij<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere: Pontificij ſperabant totam inſulam arſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bello ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vili: &amp; è tumultu aureum ſuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diem vtrique inſole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicabant. Sed fruſtratae adhuc divinâ virgulâ &amp; pruden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimis Senatorum Regni conſilijs ſunt ſpes omnium.</p>
            <p>Adhuc iuſtitia &amp; pax occurru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t inter ſe;<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> veritas &amp; fides oſculantur ſe. Regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Angliae etiamnum eſt regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lij, Regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Regis mei eſt regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Dei mei, adhuc vivit De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſor fidei à fide defenſitatus: Iuſtitiae aſſertor, &amp; in iuſtif ſimâ Regni cauſâ acceptiſſimus: pacis cultor, &amp; à pace ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultus pater Eccleſiae <hi>Iacobus,</hi> filius eiuſde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>Elizabethae</hi> hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res regnoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; virtutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Deus tibi regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, regno pietatem, pietati pacem, &amp; quidem cuncta haereditariò tradidit: vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hanc patriae noſtrae gentem, Sororem non paenè ſed plenè noſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnius parentis geminam, Religione, ſanguine, ſolo, ſolio, lingua, communibus officijs, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nibus periculis, mari vt vno muro coniunctiſſimam, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliam</hi> inquam &amp; <hi>Scotiam,</hi> ſeu vt verè dixerim, <hi>Anglia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> &amp; <hi>Sociam</hi> vno aureo &amp; amabiliſſimo rectionis tuae nexu in aeternu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, niſi peccata noſtra interverta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, colligavit.<note place="margin">Cicero. of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fic. 2.</note> 
               <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> execrari ſolebat eos qui vtile et honeſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> naturâ cohae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rentia, animis ſegregabant. <hi>Chriſtus</hi> maior <hi>Socrate</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natur:<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th 19 6. Eph. 2.14.</note> 
               <hi>Ne homo ſeparet quod Deus coniunxit.</hi> Paries inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerinus inter haec duo regna, te regnante, Dei digito re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſit. <hi>Iſraelem</hi> &amp; <hi>Iudam</hi> in te fecit vnum: non duo regna amplius, nec duos reges: non duos paſtores, nec duos gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:
<pb facs="tcp:4475:5"/>
non duas gentes, nec duas mentes: no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> duas regiones, nec duas religiones. Vnus Rex, vnus grex, vna lex, &amp; vt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat ab initio,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 82.</note> vna <hi>Albio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Omnia in vno deo caeleſti vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. om nia in vno deo terreſtri, (<hi>dixi vos deos,</hi> ait ſcriptura) vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:
<q>
                  <note place="margin">Homer.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Quocirca vtere, auguſtiſſime monarcha, hac magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia tua, potire, fruere: Sparta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> nactus es, parte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turae iure tuam optima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adorna: macte iſta virtute regia: perge porro initiorum laude egregia: Deum tanto bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiorum cumulo admirabiliter Deum tuum, eiuſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> Reg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his ipſis Regni primordijs, ſe data iam peſte et pate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factis coniuratoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſilijs, perfecto corde, totiſ<expan>
                  <am>
                     <g ref="char:abque"/>
                  </am>
                  <ex>que</ex>
               </expan> viribus impenſiùs, ſi fieri poteſt, quaerito: Religionem non illibata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſolum tuere, ſed adauge: Eva<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gelium per omnes oras pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagato: Artes &amp; Academias honeſtato: <hi>Chriſti</hi> patrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium amplificato: vt Deo è poſtliminio reddatur, quod Dei eſt, vbicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>que tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt avita iura in Eccleſia, in Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica, niſi quid ex <hi>Adamo,</hi> aut <hi>Romulo</hi> faecis co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>traximus, rata &amp; grata eſſe iube: iuſtitia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnibus imperato: tenuiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verò acciſas res in proſequenda lite ſublevato: non con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taxat, ſed arctiſſimam amicitiam inter ſororias has gentes &amp; earum conſobrinos omnes, firmiter modis omnibus conſtabilito: Recipe nos denique &amp; noſtros in clientelam tuam: vt Deo ſemper co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cinamus ſacru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paeana &amp; alleluiah: inter nos autem de te circumſonemus: vivat, vincat, vigeat, valeat, floreat diutiſſimè <hi>Iacobus</hi> Rex <hi>Ang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia, Scotia, Galliae</hi> &amp; <hi>Hiberniae</hi> cum ſereniſſima Domina <hi>Anna</hi> Regina vxore cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>He<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>rico</hi> filio <hi>VValliae</hi> Principe, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tota reliqua regali ſobole: viuat inquam <hi>Iacobus Anglia</hi> Rex &amp; <hi>Scotiae,</hi> ſeu vt vno verbo dicam, <hi>Britanniae.</hi> dixi.</p>
         </div>
         <div xml:lang="eng" type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:4475:5"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> 
               <hi>wil giue</hi> ſaith the Lord by noſea the prophet,<note place="margin">Oſe 2.15.</note> 
               <hi>the vale of</hi> Achor <hi>for the gate of hope.</hi> Now the vale of <hi>Achor</hi> was the firſt entraunce for the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Iſrael</hi> into the land of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. Semblably this fort of the Tower (O mighty King) is the thre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold, as it were, of the land of your beheſt: and the firſt ſtep of your inveſtiture vnto a king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, determined vnto you by divine decree, before you were borne. At the porte gates whereof there ſaluteth you by my words, not only your faithfull Lieuetenant a Knight graced with ornaments of warre and peace,<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</note> and the whole troop of armed men, that ſurrou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d your prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſon, your ſervants the Gard in this place: but togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo there welcomes you, as it were with one obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, whole <hi>England, Fraunce</hi> &amp; <hi>Ireland,</hi> the ſoveraigne authority of all which by the poſſeſſion of this one place, you do claſpe and as it were gripe in your hand. For this Tower and royal Caſtle is the pledge for them all, &amp; not onely the gate of good hope, but the haven of the whole ſcope.<note place="margin">The Lyons</note> Here the ſtately and princely beaſtes the <hi>Lyons (couchant)</hi> of <hi>England</hi> do bow downe to the <hi>Lyon (Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pant)</hi> of <hi>Scotland:</hi> even to you a true ofſpring of the Lyon of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and rightly diſcended of Kings your great-great grandfathers. Here is mony coyned,<note place="margin">The mynt.</note> the ioints &amp; ſinewes of warre, which now a good while ſince hath borne the image and ſuperſcription of you our Caeſar. Here are the
<pb facs="tcp:4475:6"/>
Records of Eſtate,<note place="margin">Records.</note> the cloſet of the acts &amp; patents of our princes, your renowned progenitors, out of which, I may boldly avouch it, a truer ſtory of our nation by far may be compiled, then any is yet extant. Here are diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſeverall quarters of this place,<note place="margin">Priſons.</note> certaine rounde turrets for the cuſtody of offendors againſt the king. This which is next,<note place="margin">Bloody Tower.</note> our elders tearmed the bloody Tower, for the bloodſhed, as they ſay, of thoſe Infant Princes of <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> the fourth, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Richard</hi> the third of curſed memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (I ſhudder to men<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion it,) ſavagely killed two togither at one time. Then there preſente h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e looking duti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully from a great heigth vpon you,<note place="margin">Square Tower.</note> but holding out bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen pieces of ſhot, threatning ſlaſhings of fire and thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derbolts to your enemies, a great and ſquare Tower for martiall ſervice, the ſtrength of this place, a watchman for the City, a keeper of the peace, a commaunder of the country round about,<note place="margin">Caeſars hall</note> wherein antiquity hath eſpecially made memorable the hall of the Romaine Caeſar. Here is the Iewell-houſe and the wealth of the kingdome,<note place="margin">The Iewell houſe.</note> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining implements of great valew aboue number, and al the gold and ſilver plate,<note place="margin">The War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drop.</note> with a moſt rich princely war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drop; all which haue now long ſince powred themſelues into your boſome, as the iuſt owner &amp; ful heire to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al. Here are, that I may not name every thing, mou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines of bullets, and moſt large places aboue and below for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt of armour,<note place="margin">Armory.</note> with ordinance, dartes, pikes, bowes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, privy coats, helmets, gun-powder, finally with the whole furniture of chivalry, for ſervice on horſe, on foot, by land by ſea, exceedingly ſtoared: (&amp; all theſe) to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due your enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to defend your friends, citizens, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, aſſociats and confederats: and to propulſe danger, annoyance, violence, feare from your owne perſon (moſt
<pb facs="tcp:4475:6"/>
puiſſant King) from your deareſt ſpouſe, our Soveraigne Queene, your progeny, eſtate, and whole traine. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we giue thankes as many as our heart can conceiue, to him firſt, by whom Kings raigne,<note place="margin">Pro. 8.15.</note> by whom your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, O <hi>Iames</hi> a ſixt among others, to vs a firſt, in this ſixt age of the world, in your owne conſtant age, in the decly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning age of our kingdome, doth enter your raigne &amp; now fully raigneth: and the rather, that in ſo great ods of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, ſo many ſects cutting from one another, ſuch diſtractions of mens mindes, you doe with ſuch wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full agreement of all degrees, every one acclaming to it, no man reclaiming at it, and without any ſtirring of wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſo peaceably raigne. There is no country, burrough, precinct, city, hamlet, out of which there haue not come openly of al ſorts, ages, degrees, of al eſtates &amp; conditions even from the moſt vtmoſt foreine parts, embaſſadors to congratulate. What wonderfull reſorte out of good townes: what concourſe out of the field country of far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers with their wiues &amp; children, as though ſome great &amp; feſtivall day of the everliving God were now celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. So that there was not a more dutifull ſtriving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Iuda</hi> to bring home <hi>David</hi> there king:<note place="margin">2. Sam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9.</note> then there is ready obſequiouſnes of the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England</hi> as of one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for the bringing in of our <hi>David</hi> a King after Gods owne hart. For theſe two orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of arts and armes, which in <hi>David</hi> were eminent, namely the praiſe of holy learning to the height of a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, the honour of victorious exploits abroad in warre: theſe two do begin to ſhew themſelues to bee with you: who without warre vanquiſhing the prowde, haue vpon the hearing of your name attained vnto moſt mighty kingdomes: and haue written ſuch worthy golde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bookes
<pb facs="tcp:4475:7"/>
out of the circle of ſacred ſciences, &amp; the finer learning, that good literature which, as vulgar, lay deſpiſed, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth now to be ennobled, and by your raigne to raigne it ſelfe. And verely as the ſonne is brighter then, when it is in the midſt of heaven, then whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is in any other part: ſo the ſhine of learning is both more orient, and the fruite more abundant in a king, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in any other eſtate of men: ſeeing thereby he may bee preſident in the courts of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and chiefe moderator in ſchooles; (as of late you were to al our glory:) both to diſcerne the right with your owne eies, and alſo to foſter learning, and to favour lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men much more. And although we cannot but bee affected with the miſſe of (now) S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> (our late Queene) yet ſeing, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſhe, as our ſunne ſetting &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs in the ripe time of her daies, there follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſo ſhort and ſo cleare a night enlightened with ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtarres of the kingdome,<note place="margin">The milke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> way in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven diverſe philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers haue called S. Iames way. The laſt conſpiracy.</note> chalking out one kings way, as the milken way in heaven, plainely (as the olde ſawe hath bin) S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iames</hi> way: and ſeeing another ſunne roſe ſo carely vnto vs, by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort whereof this whole now a yeare almoſt hath continued as one faire day, without any ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my cloud towards, but ſuch an one, as vaniſhed in the verie gathering of it through the protection of God: ſo that in this change we feele no alteration fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the raygne of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> neither may we expect any other thinges at your Maieſties hands, but even all the good things of Queene <hi>Elizabethes</hi> time, ſaving that your ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proweſſe, and the induments of nature in the ſuperior degree of your ſex aboue her, doth promiſe both greater and more notable attempts:<note place="margin">Apoc. 19.16.</note> Vnto God (firſt) in <hi>whoſe thigh is written King of Kinges and Lord of Lordes</hi> (the chiefe Prince among al your imperial electors (for it was
<pb facs="tcp:4475:7"/>
the doing of divine power and not humane) with moſt thankful mindes we yeeld our ſelues, and next in you, O ſacred King the annointed of the Lord, we ſet our hearts at reſt. For this is the ſhouting and triumphant applauſe of al your ſubiectes, that ioyntly welcome you vnto the crowne.</p>
            <q>
               <l>The cry of people ſounds alike, yet is their voice all one:<note place="margin">Martial.</note>
               </l>
               <l>Thou <hi>Iames</hi> our King, of country art, the father term'd alone.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Wherefore take vnto you, the triumphs of peace: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue (here) the keyes of the kingdome: take into your hand the helme of this Empire: Enter into the poſſeſſion of the chamber of your kingdome, the chiefe citty Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don: goe vp into the chiefe fort of your land, the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall armour houſe of the Realme; this Tower of London. <hi>Ireland</hi> wiſely foreſeeing your approach, partly ſubdued, partly yeelding, is become totally yours. The two Roſes of <hi>England,</hi> both the red Roſe of <hi>Lancaſter,</hi> rightly called ruddie, as beeing embrued in blood by wounds from her ſelfe, til ſhee was almoſt ſpent: and that other white Roſe of the houſe of <hi>Yorke,</hi> rightly named white, as which ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving loſt much blood by civil warre waxed pale wel nigh vnto death: which both with their prickles ſtinging togi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encountered oftener then was fitte with the Lion of <hi>Scotland;</hi> do now offer themſelues as coronets &amp; garla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds about your head. As though God had now fulfilled that, which he foreſpake by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> to this purpoſe:<note place="margin">Ezech. 37.16.</note> 
               <hi>Sonne of man take vnto thee two pieces of wood; write in one to</hi> Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huda: <hi>in the other write To</hi> Ioſeph <hi>with al the houſe of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael: <hi>Then frame them togither in one, that they may be one in thy hand. For thus ſaith the Lord. I wil take the houſe of</hi> Ioſeph <hi>with the tribes of</hi> Iſrael, <hi>&amp; the houſe of</hi> Iuda <hi>with
<pb facs="tcp:4475:8"/>
his tribes, and wil ioyne them by one fabricke in my hand, &amp; will make them one nation, and one king, namely</hi> David <hi>my ſervant ſhall be Paſtor over them neither ſhall they be anie more two nations, nor henceforth devided into two king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms</hi> &amp;c. who doth not ſee &amp; loue the like proceeding of God with vs? The wicked, the deſperate ruffins thought in the cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge to caſt all in a hurly-burly: the Popiſh crue hoped that the whole Iland would haue bin on fire with civil warre &amp; both of them out of the midſt of the ſturre, did gloriouſly bragge of their golden day. But through the rod of Gods providence over vs, and by the prudent advice of the counſelors of eſtate, al their hopes hitherto haue beene made fruſtrate:<note place="margin">Pſal. 85.10.</note> 
               <hi>Yet iuſtice and peace do greete togither truth &amp; faithfulnes do kiſſe each other:</hi> the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England</hi> is ſtill the kingdome of the Goſpell: the kingdome of my king is the kingdome of my God: yet there liveth the Defender of the faith, defended by the faith: the mainteiner of Iuſtice, and moſt acceptably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained in his moſt iuſt title to the kingdome: a promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of peace &amp; promoted by peace, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Iames</hi> the father of the church, &amp; ſonne of the ſame: the heire of Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in her kingdomes and vertues. God hath given vnto you a kingdome: vnto the kingdome a holy Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: to a holy Religion peace: and all theſe to you even by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance. This neighbour nation to our natiue country, not out halfe but full ſiſter, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it were a twinne of the ſame mother, moſt neere of al other to one another in Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in blood, in ſoile, in right of crowne, in language, in common ſervices, and common hazardes, ſurrounded with one ſea as one wall, I meane <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to ſpeake more truely, <hi>One land,</hi> hath God plotted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to one by the golden and moſt loving knotte of your go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement:
<pb facs="tcp:4475:8"/>
and that if our ſinnes doe not overturne it, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for ever. <hi>Socrates</hi> was wont to curſe them,<note place="margin">Cicero. offic. 2.</note> who ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red honeſty and profit a ſunder in their purpoſes, which by nature cleave togither. <hi>Chriſt</hi> greater then <hi>Socrates</hi> doth command; <hi>Let no man ſeperate,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 19.6.</note> 
               <hi>that which God hath ioined togither.</hi> The partition wall betweene theſe two kingdomes by the finger of God at your comming to the crowne is gone: he hath made <hi>Iſrael and Iuda one</hi> in you:<note place="margin">Eph. 2.14.</note> no more two kingdomes, nor two kings: nor two paſtors, nor two flockes: nor two kindes nor two mindes: nor two Regions, nor two Religions. One King, one people, one law, and as it was in the beginning, one land of <hi>Albion.</hi> Al things in one heavenly God one: al things in one earthly God, (<hi>for I have stiled you Gods,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm. 82.</note> as the ſcripture ſpeaketh) One.
<q>
                  <l>It is not good that in any heads beare rule in any land:<note place="margin">Homer.</note>
                  </l>
                  <l>Let one be ſoveraigne King and Lord, and ſo decrees may ſtand.</l>
               </q>
Wherfore moſt mighty monarch, make vſe of this your magnificent eſtate; poſſeſſe it, enioy it; bewtifie this your portion, even your beſt inheritance, which you are come vnto by right of nature: proceed on in your princely ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue: go forward in the worthy praiſe of theſe beginnings: Seeke that God, which is become your God wonderful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by ſuch a heape of benefits, and his kingdome alſo in this beginning of your kingdome, the plague beeing much abated, and the counſels of conſpirators detected, e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en with a perfit hart and with all your power, even yet more earneſtly, if it may be. Not only preſerve religion, but increaſe it: Plant the Goſpel throughout all your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions: Give reputatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to Arts &amp; Vniverſitie, Enlarge the patrimony of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> that now at le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth after long de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue, reſtitutio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may be made vnto God of al that is due
<pb facs="tcp:4475:9"/>
vnto God, wherſoever you haue to do. Confirme &amp; rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the auncient lawes both in Church and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, except where we haue gathered any corruption, either from <hi>Adam or Rome:</hi> Command iuſtice to all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but eaſe the lowe eſtate of the poore in following their ſuites Eſtabliſh ſtrongly by al meanes not only concord, but indiſſoluble frendſhip betweene theſe ſiſter natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and all the ſiſters children: Finally receive vs and ours in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your protection; that we may alway ſing vnto God a holy himne, &amp; alleluiah, &amp; of you may ſtil ring this peale among our ſelues: <hi>Let live, O God, let vanquiſh, let growe, let proſper, let flouriſh, as long, as mortality may endure, eve<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Iames <hi>of</hi> England, Scotland, Fraunce <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>King, togither with our ſoveraigne Ladie</hi> Anne, <hi>his ſpouſe; with</hi> Henry <hi>Prince of</hi> Wales, <hi>and the reſt of the royal Progeny: Let liue I ſay</hi> Iames <hi>of</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>or to ſpeake at one word, King of whole</hi> Brittaine.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:4475:9"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
